Finding Aid for Shaw Family (Shiawassee County, Mich.) papers, 1877-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Shaw Family (Shiawassee County, Mich.) papers 1877-1977
Shaw family.
85531 Aa 2; AA
Papers, 1877-1926, of William Shaw, physician in Morrice, Michigan, including diaries, notebooks, and records of patient appointments and accounts; patient books, 1884-1891, of brother, Alexander Shaw, physician in Watertown, Dakota (later South Dakota); papers, 1907-1977, of Milton Shaw, son of William Shaw, Lansing physician including correspondence, diaries, professional files, and materials relating to medical career in the military, especially letters written during World War I; and photographs.
3 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1978 and 1979 by Eleanor A. Shaw (donor no. 6235 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Many of the members of the Shaw family of Shiawassee County, Michigan were physicians. Dr. William Shaw (1851-1932) was a longtime physician of Morrice, Shiawassee County, Michigan and an 1891 graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School. Dr. Alex Shaw was an 1882 graduate of McGill University and practiced at Bancroft, Shiawassee County, Michigan, and Watertown, Dakota (later South Dakota). Dr. William Shaw was a 1914 graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School. During World War I, he served as a medical officer with the 32nd Division in France and held commissions through World War II as officer or medical inspector with the Michigan National Guard, the Michigan State Troops, and the Selective Service.
The Shaw family papers date from 1877 to 1977 and contain materials principally relating to the medical careers of three family members. Included are 25 volumes (1892-1926) containing patient appointments and accounts of Dr. William Shaw. Among his other papers are diaries and notebooks pertaining to his early career in the schools at Motherwell, Ontario, Canada where he taught for eleven years from about 1877 to 1888. Also included in the collection are the patient books of Dr. Alexander Shaw (1854-1892), brother of Dr. William Shaw. There is one folder of correspondence written by Harold Shaw, a son of Dr. William Shaw, to his parents during World War I while serving with the 85th Division.
The papers of Dr. Milton Shaw (1889-1977), another son of Dr. William Shaw, constitute the principal part of the collection and reflect his active professional career. His papers include correspondence to his parents from France during the First World War as well as materials concerning the other phases of his military career including his involvement with several veterans organizations. Dr. Milton Shaw's connections with professional and service organizations were numerous and involved positions on the governing boards of the Michigan Welfare League and the Michigan Heart Association as well as the Directorships of the University of Michigan Alumni Association (1946-1949) and the Ingham County Chapter of the American Red Cross (1933).
Subjects:
American National Red Cross. Ingham County Chapter.; Dakota Territory.; Ingham County Medical Society.; Lansing (Mich.); Medicine--Michigan--Morrice.; Michigan Heart Association.; Michigan Welfare League.; Morrice (Mich.); Physicians--Michigan--Lansing.; Physicians--South Dakota--Watertown.; Physicians--Michigan--Morrice.; Red Cross and Red Crescent--Michigan--Ingham County.; Shiawassee County (Mich.); University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Artillery.; Canoes.; France.; Graduation ceremonies.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Medical education.; Nurses.; Shaw, Milton, 1889-1977.; Shaw, William, 1851-1932.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery. Class of 1891.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery. Class of 1914.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Anniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1911-1920.; Veterans--Michigan.; War casualties.; War damage.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Shaw, Alexander, 1854-1892.; Shaw, Milton, 1889-1977.; Shaw, William, 1851-1932.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family papers
  - John Shaw (b. 1838), brother of Dr. William Shaw
    - Correspondence 1852-1896 and phrenological chart (Box 1)
  - Dr. William Shaw (1851-1932)
    - Biographical and miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Ledger 1905-1908 (Box 1)
    - Diaries and notebooks
      - 1877 Diary and notebook (Box 1)
      - 1878 Diary, with notes, 1878-1880 (Box 1)
      - January 1879 Diary, with notes 1879, 1883 and accounts 1890 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1881 Notebook (Box 1)
      - 1891 Medical school clinical notebook (Box 1)
      - 1895 Notebook (Box 1)
      - 1897-1900 Notebook, with 1897 accounts and 1899-1900 orders (Box 1)
    - Visiting Lists (patient appointments and accounts), 25 volumes
      - February 1892-February 1893 (with notes) (Box 1)
      - February-April 1893 (Box 1)
        (with notes 1892-1893)
      - 1893 (with cash accounts) (Box 1)
      - 1894 (Box 1)
      - 1895-1896 (Box 1)
      - 1902-1903 (with teaching notes) (Box 1)
      - 1903 (with tuition accounts) (Box 1)
      - 1904 (Box 1)
      - 1905 (Box 1)
      - 1906 (Box 1)
      - 1907-January 1908 (Box 1)
      - 1908-July 1909 (Box 1)
      - Aug 1909-January 1910 (with appointments and accounts (Box 1)
      - January-July 1892 (Box 1)
      - 1910-September 1911 (with notes to December 1911) (Box 1)
      - October 1911-January 1912 (Box 1)
        (with notes 1900-1902)
      - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
      - 1914-1915 (Box 1)
      - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
      - 1918 (with notes) (Box 1)
      - 1918-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1921 (Box 1)
      - 1922-July 1923 (Box 1)
      - 1924-September 1926 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Alexander Shaw (1854-1892), brother of Dr. William Shaw
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Ledger 1885-1886 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Lists (patient appointments and accounts), 6 volumes
      - 1884 (Box 1)
      - 1886 (Box 1)
      - 1887 (Box 1)
      - 1888 (Box 1)
      - 1889 (Box 1)
      - 1891 (Box 1)
  - Harold Shaw), son of Dr. William Shaw
    - Correspondence May-November 1918 (Box 2)
  - Dr. Milton Shaw (1889-1977), son of Dr. William Shaw
    - Biographical and personal (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated 1907-1916 (Box 2)
      - February-August 1918 (Box 2)
      - September-December 1918 (Box 2)
      - 1919 (Box 2)
      - 1920-1922 (Box 2)
      - 1923-1977 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous family correspondence (Box 2)
    - Military career
      - World War I service records (Box 2)
      - 32nd Division Veterans' Association, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 119th Field Artillery Veterans' Association
        - Papers (Box 2)
        - Rosters 1941-1970 (incomplete), 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan National Guard, Michigan State Troops and (Box 2)
      - Selective Service (Box 2)
      - Michigan National Guard Officers' rosters (Box 2)
      - Michigan Council of Defense, Citizens' Defense Corps 1942 (Box 2)
      - Military Order of Foreign Wars
        - National Commandery (Box 2)
        - Michigan Commandery (Box 2)
    - Professional activities
      - National associations (Box 2)
      - Michigan State Medical Society (Box 2)
      - Ingham County Medical Society, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - St. Lawrence Hospital (Box 2)
    - Organizational files
      - University of Michigan Alumni Association, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - American Red Cross, Ingham County Chapter, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Heart Association 1952-1960, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Youth Commission circa 1950 (Box 2)
      - Michigan Welfare League
        - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
        - 1952-1953, 1956 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Ingham County organizations (Box 2)
    - Dr. Reuben L. Kahn (Box 2)
    - Writings (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Lansing related materials (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Memorandum books of births registered 1916-1926 (scattered), 3 volumes (Box 3)
    - Cash books 1910-1915, 2 volumes (Box 3)
    - Journal October 1916-March 1921 (Box 3)
    - Diaries 1909, 1913-1919, 1923, 1925-1971, 1973-January 1977, 60 volumes (Box 3)
    - Daybook (medical practice) December 1916-July 1917, October 1919-December 1920 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook 1950s (mostly re: Ingham County physicians) (Box 3)
- Family Photographs
  - Family and friends (Box 3)
  - Groups
    - Alumni and professional (Box 3)
    - Students (Box 3)
  - Medical School, 2 folders (Box 3)
    (includes 1 photo of William Shaw's graduating class)
  - Military
    - France (Box 3)
    - U.S. (training and reunions) (Box 3)
  - Portraits and snapshots (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan student album (Volume 1)
    (includes student activities and canoeing on the Huron River)